A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests, Series F FA315
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests, Series F
1894-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, David
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Rockefeller, Winthrop
FA315
28 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Scope and Contents note
The material in this series deals with the topics of industrial reform, unionization, development in the Third World, employment, AIA, Chambers of Commerce, the 1939 New York World's Fair, and Industrial Relations Counselors.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Medical education; Medical research; Maternal health services; Medical care; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; International education; International relations; Performing arts; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Public policy; Public health administration; Public health; Prohibition; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Urban policy; Urban renewal; World War I; World War II; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Travel; United States; Philanthropy -- United States; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; Religion; Public welfare; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Folk art; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Art; Economic development; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Business; Arts; Capital investments; Philanthropy; Business enterprises, Foreign; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Civic improvement; Child welfare; International economic relations; International cooperation; China Medical Board (U.S); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Spelman Fund; Rockefeller Foundation; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Center; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Spelman family; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Standard Oil Company; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; International Education Board; Sealantic Fund, New York; Rockefeller University; Davison Fund
- American Association for Labor Legislation, 1910-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to Association for betterment of working conditions. Support ends when Starr J. Murphy questions "radicalism" of members of Association. Shows Rockefellers' support of basic human needs, but their staff's suspicion of unions or union advocates. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, H. R. Seager, John B. Andrews.
  File Plan note
  7
- American Breeder's Association, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Group doing eugenics studies; studied inherited diseases, longevity, inheritance of mental disease. John D. Rockefeller support nominal; Starr J. Murphy the interested party. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, C. B. Davenport.
  92
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - Certificate of Incorporation - By Laws, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Copy of Certificate.
  97
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - General, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Nelson A. Rockefeller describes purpose of AIA to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. cautions Nelson A. Rockefeller about his own involvement in program; urges him to investigate Rockefeller Foundation tie-in. Office space; press releases. Nelson A. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd gifts to AIA; comments on AIA. Reports on progress of program; development of Indian cooperatives program. John D. Rockefeller 3rd resigned as director, 1957. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller, Rodman C. Rockefeller.
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - General, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - General, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  General note
  Open per KWR, August 30, 2006.
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Contributions, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $500,000.
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - Nelson A. Rockefeller Trip to Brazil and Mexico, November 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Expenses, associates.
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation, 1946-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Nelson A. Rockefeller gifts to International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC). Policy on charitable giving. J. Jennen's trip to Brazil. David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd purchase stock in IBEC. IBEC stock issue, investments, projects. Rodman C. Rockefeller elected director, 1959. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, L-H. Levy.
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 0008A)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation (Box 1, Folder 0008AA)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 0008B)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation Research Institute, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Gift to International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Research Institute (IRI) by Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller and Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Report on research projects and programs. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
  97.1
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation Research Institute, 1950-1961 (Box 2, Folder 0009A)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation - Financing and Stock Subscriptions, 1946-1956 (Box 2, Folder 0009B)
  Rockefeller family investment in International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC). Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauz.
  97.1F
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - International Basic Economy Corporation (Box 2, Folder 0009BA)
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development - Venezuela Basic Economy Corporation, 1947-1955 (Box 2, Folder 0009C)
  Nelson A. Rockefeller memo on trip to Venezuela. Reports on Venezuelan program. New York investments of Venezuela Basic Economy Corporation (VBEC). Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, John Camp.
  97.2
- American Mining Congress, 1914-1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Secretary of American Mining Congress asks John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to participate in Congress work. Contact initiated as result of John D. Rockefeller's position in the Colorado Fuel & Iron affair. Raymond B. Fosdick interested in Congress; Ivy Lee advised against participation. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declines to participate. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, J. F. Callbreath (Secretary AMC), Ivy Lee.
  86
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Profit Sharing Plans, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Mostly copies of plans for profit sharing by several companies, including Dennison Company (Framingham, Massachusetts), Equitable Trust Company, General Motors, Imperial Oil, Deere & Company (Moline, Illinois), James McCreery & Company, International Harvester, Columbia Trust Company, Bergen Point Iron Works, American Linseed - Colorado Fuel & Iron, Standard Oil of New York, United States Steel, other Standard Oil Companies. Some Rockefeller opinions in folder on Standard Oil Companies; 1931 comments (anonymous) on profit-sharing plans.
  156
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Profit Sharing Plans, 1918-1921, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Profit Sharing Plans - Standard Oil Employees, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Profit Sharing Plans - Printed Material, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 0013A)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Bonuses and Additional Salaries, 1916-1919 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Payment of bonuses (cost of living) to Foundation, Institute, General Education Board (GEB) and Bureau employees. Information on bonus policies of other firms and foundations. Stopped with end of war. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  156.1
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Bonuses and Additional Salaries, 1916-1919 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Pension Plans, 1909-1950 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Pension plans from John D. Rockefeller 3rd's office, and various other firms. Ministers Pension Fund (1909-1919); discussion of possible pension fund for ministers--vetoed by Frederick T. Gates and Bullrick, gradual agreement from Starr J. Murphy. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, Starr J. Murphy.
  156.2
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Minister's Pension Plan, 1909-1919 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Pension Plans, 1909-1950 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Council of Profit Sharing Industries, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Nephew of E. P. Prentice tried to interest family in council; no success. Correspondents include Sartell Prentice, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  156.3
- Bonus and Profit Sharing Plans - Council of Profit Sharing Industries, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Brotherhood of Men and Nations - General, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s address at Chatauqua Assembly, August 10, 1918. Also given in revised form at Canadian Club, Ottawa, Ontario, April 13, 1918; and at Civic and Commercial Club Dinner, June 13, 1918. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  190
- Brotherhood of Men and Nations - Address Delivered Before The Canadian Club of Ottawa, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 0021A)
- Chamber of Commerce - General, 1912-1960 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest in Chamber's work. Federal Reserve Bill; anti-Red program 1919-1921; reactions to Stewart case. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. comments on issues; dinners. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller.
  56
- Chamber of Commerce - Membership Dues and Contributions, 1920-1960 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to Chamber.
- Chamber of Commerce - New Building, 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to Chamber of Commerce building.
- Chamber of Commerce - "Nation's Business", 1912-1952 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest in publication. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
- Chamber of Commerce - Cleveland, 1894-1960 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  John D. Rockefeller a life member; small donations; invitations to speak. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. elected an active member. Copy of Sargent portrait of John D. Rockefeller given to Chamber in 1920. Withdrawal of family interest. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  56C
- Chamber of Commerce - Downtown Lower Manhattan Association, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 0026A)
  W. T. Lindquist executive office of organization, represented David Rockefeller Program for World Trade Center. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, W. T. Lindquist.
  56D
- Chamber of Commerce - Downtown Lower Manhattan Association, 1956-1977 (Box 4, Folder 0026B)
- Chamber of Commerce - Downtown Lower Manhattan Association - International Downtown Executives Association, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 0026C)
- Chamber of Commerce - Empire State Association of Commerce, Inc., 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Decision not to join upstate Association. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. wrote to many oil firms urging them to join or increase their contribution to the Association. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., R. M. Mansfield.
  56E
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce, 1912-1961 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  W. W. Aldrich president of Chamber; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. an associate member. Chamber's program, invitations to dinners. David Rockefeller a trustee of American Council of International Chamber of Commerce. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  56I
  Closed material moved to Folder 28A by KWR, August 30, 2006.
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce (Box 4, Folder 0028A)
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1955-1960 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  John D. Rockefeller 3rd's study for United States Council of business potential in Asia. Background of study; government assistance; assembling staff. Impact of economic policy on Cold War; role of private enterprise in the economic development of Asia. International Chamber of Commerce convention in Tokyo refused to endorse report: reason given was too much emphasis on government activity. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, D. McLean, Staff members.
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Tokyo Conference, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  Report submitted and refused here; john D. Rockefeller 3rd did not attend.
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Report, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  Drafts of sections of report "United States Economic Policy - Asia." Two copies of final report. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, E. C. Hagen.
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Report, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Report, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Chamber of Commerce - International Chamber of Commerce - United States Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Report, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Chamber of Commerce - Japanese Chamber of Commerce in New York, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Statements on Japanese trade with United States. John D. Rockefeller 3rd a member of Chamber. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  56J
- Chambers of Commerce - Miscellaneous, 1957-1961 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  John D. Rockefeller 3rd a member of Virginia State Chamber of Commerce until 1956. Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd decline requests for contribution to Junior International Chamber. Refusals to speak at Chamber of Commerce dinners. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, D. McLean.
  56M
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1897-1960 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  Chamber's position on national and state issues; invitations to banquets. Rockefeller contributions to projects. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. acting president 1948-1949; John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. vice presidents. All of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s sons and Rodman C. Rockefeller members. Komlosy portrait of John D. Rockefeller given to Chamber in 1903, replaced by copy of Sargent portrait in 1921. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., R. Mansfield.
  56N
  DR material moved to Folder 37A by KWR, August 30, 2006.
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York (Box 6, Folder 0037A)
  David Rockefeller was vice president. Copy of Salisbury portrait of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. given in 1959 by David Rockefeller. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1897-1960 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  DR material removed to Folder 38A.
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1897-1960 (Box 6, Folder 0038A)
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1897-1960 (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - City Affairs Committee, 1897-1934 (Box 6, Folder 0039A)
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - City Affairs Committee, 1935-1946 (Box 6, Folder 0039B)
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - City Affairs Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 6, Folder 0039C)
  David Rockefeller served on Committee, 1953-1954; not very active. Resigned. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, W. Lindquist.
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - City Affairs Committee - Water Supply, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  David Rockefeller avoids taking position on use of Harlem River water for city supply. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
- Chamber of Commerce - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Honorary Membership, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  John D. Rockefeller, Jr. tribute to John D. Rockefeller on being made honorary member; comments.